<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tt xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2006/10/ttaf1" xmlns:tts="http://www.w3.org/2006/10/ttaf1#style">
	<head>
    	<metadata/>
    	<styling/>
    	<layout/>
  	</head>
  	<body>
    	<div>
                       <p begin="0:00:24.960" end="0:00:30.760">There are more kinds of insects in the world than all other kinds of animals put together.</p>
                       <p begin="0:00:30.800" end="0:00:32.800">But because they are so small,</p>
                       <p begin="0:00:32.840" end="0:00:36.720">we rarely see how extraordinary they are.</p>
                       <p begin="0:00:36.760" end="0:00:41.080">Occasionally, they assemble in astonishing numbers.</p>
                       <p begin="0:00:44.560" end="0:00:49.360">A billion monarch butterflies hibernate in the forests of Mexico.</p>
                       <p begin="0:01:00.280" end="0:01:04.560">Vast clouds of mayflies emerge all at once to mate.</p>
                       <p begin="0:01:07.960" end="0:01:11.200">Insects face endless challenges.</p>
                       <p begin="0:01:12.880" end="0:01:16.440">They can transform their bodies to meet every purpose -</p>
                       <p begin="0:01:16.480" end="0:01:20.800">eyes grow onstalks. Bodies become chemical guns.</p>
                       <p begin="0:01:25.520" end="0:01:28.680">To discover how and why they do suchthings,</p>
                       <p begin="0:01:28.720" end="0:01:30.960">you have to enter theirworld.</p>
                       <p begin="0:01:54.760" end="0:02:00.760">Patagonia, Chile, home to one of the most extraordinary of beetles.</p>
                       <p begin="0:02:04.080" end="0:02:06.480">There are many kinds of beetles in the world,</p>
                       <p begin="0:02:06.520" end="0:02:10.840">but this one hassome of the biggest jaws of all.</p>
                       <p begin="0:02:10.880" end="0:02:13.680">He is Darwin's beetle.</p>
                       <p begin="0:02:16.960" end="0:02:21.000">He is on his way to the forest to look for a mate.</p>
                       <p begin="0:02:21.960" end="0:02:26.440">Whether he gets one or not will depend on his strength...</p>
                       <p begin="0:02:26.480" end="0:02:29.800">and on the size of his jaws.</p>
                       <p begin="0:02:40.120" end="0:02:42.320">He starts his search.</p>
                       <p begin="0:02:45.560" end="0:02:48.880">A female is likely to be on a tree trunk.</p>
                       <p begin="0:02:51.080" end="0:02:55.800">But trees, in this part of the world are very tall.</p>
                       <p begin="0:02:59.040" end="0:03:02.680">His search could be a long one.</p>
                       <p begin="0:03:06.760" end="0:03:12.160">Unfortunately for him, she is 25 metres above him</p>
                       <p begin="0:03:12.200" end="0:03:13.840">near the top.</p>
                       <p begin="0:03:17.520" end="0:03:21.320">She has more normal-sized jaws.</p>
                       <p begin="0:03:21.360" end="0:03:24.800">But thenshe only needs them for feeding.</p>
                       <p begin="0:03:24.840" end="0:03:28.920">But he needs immense jaws forfighting...</p>
                       <p begin="0:03:30.840" end="0:03:35.240">..because there are other males aroundwith the same mission.</p>
                       <p begin="0:03:46.800" end="0:03:51.960">Sheer strength isnot enough in these battles.</p>
                       <p begin="0:03:52.000" end="0:03:56.680">The technique is to reach over your opponent's head</p>
                       <p begin="0:03:56.720" end="0:04:00.200">and hook your jaws under his wing-covers.</p>
                       <p begin="0:04:00.240" end="0:04:03.600">That's why his jaws are so long</p>
                       <p begin="0:04:03.640" end="0:04:05.320">and have that odd shape.</p>
                       <p begin="0:04:06.880" end="0:04:08.800">He's got the grip.</p>
                       <p begin="0:04:08.840" end="0:04:11.360">Now he as to lift.</p>
                       <p begin="0:04:13.360" end="0:04:15.800">And that needs strength.</p>
                       <p begin="0:04:23.960" end="0:04:26.480">Another lift is needed.</p>
                       <p begin="0:04:37.640" end="0:04:39.640">And that's that.</p>
                       <p begin="0:04:41.360" end="0:04:45.520">Beetle armour is strong so he bounces.</p>
                       <p begin="0:04:45.560" end="0:04:48.800">The winner climbs on.</p>
                       <p begin="0:04:48.840" end="0:04:52.800">There are more males ready to fight him up here.</p>
                       <p begin="0:05:26.800" end="0:05:29.520">And here she is at last.</p>
                       <p begin="0:05:35.200" end="0:05:37.920">But she doesn't seem to be in the mood.</p>
                       <p begin="0:05:52.280" end="0:05:58.640">So now he has to use his great jaws as a restraining cage.</p>
                       <p begin="0:06:05.240" end="0:06:07.360">Success at last.</p>
                       <p begin="0:06:13.800" end="0:06:16.480">But the hurling habit dies hard.</p>
                       <p begin="0:06:23.920" end="0:06:29.960">Insects' bodies have the capacity to take on an almostinfinite variety of shapes.</p>
                       <p begin="0:06:31.160" end="0:06:35.000">This is oneof the keys to their success.</p>
                       <p begin="0:06:52.120" end="0:06:55.600">This male moth doesn't go in search of females.</p>
                       <p begin="0:06:56.680" end="0:07:00.080">He inflates a pair of scented plumes</p>
                       <p begin="0:07:00.120" end="0:07:03.320">that protrude from the end of his abdomen.</p>
                       <p begin="0:07:03.360" end="0:07:05.400">And they come to him!</p>
                       <p begin="0:07:12.520" end="0:07:16.000">All insects have the same basic design...</p>
                       <p begin="0:07:16.040" end="0:07:20.040">six legs and an armour-covered body.</p>
                       <p begin="0:07:20.080" end="0:07:22.880">But the different parts can become exaggerated</p>
                       <p begin="0:07:22.920" end="0:07:25.840">tosolve particular problems.</p>
                       <p begin="0:07:30.400" end="0:07:35.280">This beetle has a giraffe's neck in order to fight.</p>
                       <p begin="0:07:39.680" end="0:07:43.720">A praying mantis is disguised as a flower</p>
                       <p begin="0:07:43.760" end="0:07:46.920">and waits in ambush.</p>
                       <p begin="0:07:48.200" end="0:07:53.120">Another is almost invisible amongdead leaves.</p>
                       <p begin="0:07:53.160" end="0:07:59.120">Insects' armour can carry colours that can camouflage or communicate.</p>
                       <p begin="0:08:15.400" end="0:08:20.280">But the armour can also be converted into wings</p>
                       <p begin="0:08:20.320" end="0:08:22.960">and that makes insects a globalforce,</p>
                       <p begin="0:08:23.000" end="0:08:27.400">enabling them to invade almost every habitat on earth.</p>
                       <p begin="0:08:47.600" end="0:08:49.040">In Southern France,</p>
                       <p begin="0:08:49.080" end="0:08:53.640">one insect is starting on the most important day of its life.</p>
                       <p begin="0:08:57.640" end="0:09:02.080">Dawn, and a newly hatched damselfly.</p>
                       <p begin="0:09:04.640" end="0:09:08.400">She needs to mate and lay her eggs before sunset.</p>
                       <p begin="0:09:08.440" end="0:09:12.560">Her adult life is so short, she may not get another chance.</p>
                       <p begin="0:09:17.640" end="0:09:22.120">Her success will depend on these fragile wings.</p>
                       <p begin="0:09:24.960" end="0:09:27.440">She faces many perils.</p>
                       <p begin="0:09:37.960" end="0:09:41.960">Few insects can escape from a spider's web.</p>
                       <p begin="0:09:45.400" end="0:09:48.920">But her wings are more powerful thanthey look.</p>
                       <p begin="0:09:55.640" end="0:10:00.320">She wants to mate with the strongest male.</p>
                       <p begin="0:10:00.360" end="0:10:06.160">However, the stream, where she might find him, is a battle-ground.</p>
                       <p begin="0:10:13.080" end="0:10:17.600">She watches while dark-winged males compete for the best territories,</p>
                       <p begin="0:10:17.640" end="0:10:21.080">flashing their wings at each other in threat,</p>
                       <p begin="0:10:21.120" end="0:10:24.560">or trying to force their opponents into the water.</p>
                       <p begin="0:10:30.080" end="0:10:36.080">Fighting finished, the female uses her wings to signal her presence to the winner.</p>
                       <p begin="0:10:44.880" end="0:10:46.680">She won't be rushed.</p>
                       <p begin="0:10:46.720" end="0:10:50.760">But if he doesn't grip her with his tail, a rival might steal her.</p>
                       <p begin="0:10:56.960" end="0:11:02.240">As they mate, their linked bodies form the shape of a heart.</p>
                       <p begin="0:11:04.880" end="0:11:11.320">But now she has the problem of laying her fertilised eggs and that brings new hazards.</p>
                       <p begin="0:11:18.840" end="0:11:22.960">Like any athlete, she must warm her muscles for optimum performance</p>
                       <p begin="0:11:23.000" end="0:11:27.240">and does so by using her wings as solar-heating panels.</p>
                       <p begin="0:11:29.520" end="0:11:34.080">She must fly dangerously low if she's to find the right place for her eggs.</p>
                       <p begin="0:11:52.320" end="0:11:55.720">Only the quickest damselflies escape.</p>
                       <p begin="0:12:24.160" end="0:12:26.560">Safely past the frogs,</p>
                       <p begin="0:12:26.600" end="0:12:31.760">this femalehas reached a suitable planton which to lay her eggs.</p>
                       <p begin="0:12:31.800" end="0:12:35.960">But she has to place them underwater if they are to survive.</p>
                       <p begin="0:12:36.000" end="0:12:39.960">For the first time, her wings seem to be a hindrance.</p>
                       <p begin="0:12:40.000" end="0:12:42.160">But in fact, they help her yet again,</p>
                       <p begin="0:12:42.200" end="0:12:46.960">by trapping a silvery layer of air which enables her to breathe.</p>
                       <p begin="0:12:51.000" end="0:12:56.560">She cuts into a plant stem and deposits her eggs inside.</p>
                       <p begin="0:13:11.440" end="0:13:14.560">Now herwings are going to be truly tested.</p>
                       <p begin="0:13:14.600" end="0:13:19.120">If she can't break through the water surface, she will drown.</p>
                       <p begin="0:13:51.360" end="0:13:55.040">Her day has been a complete success.</p>
                       <p begin="0:13:58.280" end="0:14:03.040">Damselflies seldom venture beyond their home stream.</p>
                       <p begin="0:14:03.080" end="0:14:07.040">But some insects fly huge distances.</p>
                       <p begin="0:14:08.600" end="0:14:12.880">September on the shores of Lake Erie in Southern Canada.</p>
                       <p begin="0:14:12.920" end="0:14:17.440">A monarch butterfly is fuelling up on nectar.</p>
                       <p begin="0:14:25.440" end="0:14:28.800">A chill gust of Northerly air.</p>
                       <p begin="0:14:30.240" end="0:14:31.680">It's time to leave.</p>
                       <p begin="0:14:35.560" end="0:14:39.360">The coming winter will be so cold it would kill her.</p>
                       <p begin="0:14:46.960" end="0:14:51.360">She has never flown more than a few hundred metres in her life.</p>
                       <p begin="0:14:53.080" end="0:14:56.920">But now she is heading out over Lake Erie,</p>
                       <p begin="0:14:56.960" end="0:14:59.800">which is a hundred miles across.</p>
                       <p begin="0:15:13.400" end="0:15:18.840">This is just the first leg of one of the greatest animal migrations.</p>
                       <p begin="0:15:18.880" end="0:15:23.320">She will continue South, using thesun as a compass,</p>
                       <p begin="0:15:23.360" end="0:15:27.720">to cross America, a journey of 2,000 miles.</p>
                       <p begin="0:15:33.000" end="0:15:38.800">Her destination is Mexico and one small and special group of trees.</p>
                       <p begin="0:15:38.840" end="0:15:43.400">No-one knows how she finds them, in these great mountain forests.</p>
                       <p begin="0:15:47.360" end="0:15:52.880">She joins other monarch butterflies that have travelled here from all over North America.</p>
                       <p begin="0:15:58.240" end="0:16:01.520">Countless butterflies crowd these particular trees,</p>
                       <p begin="0:16:01.560" end="0:16:03.840">hanging from every branch.</p>
                       <p begin="0:16:13.040" end="0:16:17.040">They come here because, although winter brings a chill to the air,</p>
                       <p begin="0:16:17.080" end="0:16:21.280">there will not be a lethal freeze as there will in Canada.</p>
                       <p begin="0:16:21.320" end="0:16:24.480">The conditions are perfect for hibernation.</p>
                       <p begin="0:16:32.000" end="0:16:36.640">Hibernating butterflies are vulnerable to predators.</p>
                       <p begin="0:16:36.680" end="0:16:39.080">But monarchs are poisonous.</p>
                       <p begin="0:16:39.120" end="0:16:44.280">However, a few birds have learned to rip out the toxic parts and eat the rest.</p>
                       <p begin="0:16:44.320" end="0:16:49.160">They kill hundreds of thousands of butterflies and dislodge many more.</p>
                       <p begin="0:16:53.240" end="0:16:59.040">Those that fall must get back into the trees before nightfall brings another killer.</p>
                       <p begin="0:16:59.080" end="0:17:02.440">They vibrate their wings to warm their flight muscles.</p>
                       <p begin="0:17:02.480" end="0:17:04.680">But it's a race against time.</p>
                       <p begin="0:17:10.120" end="0:17:14.080">Night brings a lethal ground frost.</p>
                       <p begin="0:17:51.960" end="0:17:58.720">Those that do survive, sleep safely huddled together in the trees, for four months.</p>
                       <p begin="0:18:03.440" end="0:18:08.880">The warmth of spring wakes them from their hibernation.</p>
                       <p begin="0:19:21.240" end="0:19:26.240">The majority of the butterflies that flew here from Canada have survived.</p>
                       <p begin="0:19:26.280" end="0:19:31.440">They take their first drink since their arrival last autumn.</p>
                       <p begin="0:19:36.440" end="0:19:40.720">With increasing warmth, more and more butterflies awake.</p>
                       <p begin="0:19:53.560" end="0:19:56.520">Soon they will all disperse northwards</p>
                       <p begin="0:19:56.560" end="0:19:59.160">and tranquillity will return to this forest</p>
                       <p begin="0:19:59.200" end="0:20:05.960">untilthe great grandchildren of these butterflies return to escape the freezing Northern winter.</p>
                       <p begin="0:20:30.840" end="0:20:37.000">Some insects, however, have made a speciality of living in the most adverse conditions.</p>
                       <p begin="0:20:43.200" end="0:20:48.600">Mono Lake is known as California's dead sea.</p>
                       <p begin="0:20:48.640" end="0:20:54.120">It's twice as salty as the ocean and lethal to almost all life.</p>
                       <p begin="0:21:01.000" end="0:21:07.120">Alkali flies are one of the few creatures able to tolerate these conditions</p>
                       <p begin="0:21:07.160" end="0:21:09.880">and since they have virtually no competitors,</p>
                       <p begin="0:21:09.920" end="0:21:12.320">they swarm in their millions.</p>
                       <p begin="0:21:33.960" end="0:21:38.400">Flies are one of the most successful of all insects.</p>
                       <p begin="0:21:38.440" end="0:21:41.360">There are 85,000 different kinds</p>
                       <p begin="0:21:41.400" end="0:21:46.800">and among them, a perfect fly for almost every habitat, even this one.</p>
                       <p begin="0:22:03.840" end="0:22:09.960">The alkali fly has special abilities that enable it to live on this lake.</p>
                       <p begin="0:22:10.000" end="0:22:12.560">It can walk underwater to eat algae.</p>
                       <p begin="0:22:12.600" end="0:22:16.840">Fine hairs trap air bubbles that prevent it from drowning.</p>
                       <p begin="0:22:16.880" end="0:22:20.920">But most critically, the flyhas a physiology</p>
                       <p begin="0:22:20.960" end="0:22:24.680">that can neutralise the lethal levels of salt.</p>
                       <p begin="0:22:24.720" end="0:22:30.680">So the alkali fly's dominance of Mono Lake goes unchallenged</p>
                       <p begin="0:22:30.720" end="0:22:34.160">except for a few weeks of the year.</p>
                       <p begin="0:22:43.480" end="0:22:49.200">100,000Wilson's phalarope are migrating to South America.</p>
                       <p begin="0:22:49.240" end="0:22:52.600">Mono Lake is their only stop-over.</p>
                       <p begin="0:22:52.640" end="0:22:58.040">These alkali flies, for them, are an invaluable and irresistible feast.</p>
                       <p begin="0:23:05.240" end="0:23:11.600">A fly has no defence, except tofly and become lost in a vast swarm.</p>
                       <p begin="0:23:17.080" end="0:23:21.800">It needs considerable skill to pluck an individual fly from the air.</p>
                       <p begin="0:23:26.680" end="0:23:28.240">There are gulls are here, too.</p>
                       <p begin="0:23:32.280" end="0:23:36.760">Though their fly-catching techniques are not so refined.</p>
                       <p begin="0:24:05.640" end="0:24:09.840">In four weeks, the phalaropes double their weight.</p>
                       <p begin="0:24:09.880" end="0:24:13.360">Then they set off again, heading south.</p>
                       <p begin="0:24:13.400" end="0:24:16.360">Leaving the gulls behind.</p>
                       <p begin="0:24:20.560" end="0:24:25.640">The size of the fly population has scarcely been affected.</p>
                       <p begin="0:24:25.680" end="0:24:29.440">For them, sheer abundance is defence enough.</p>
                       <p begin="0:24:29.480" end="0:24:32.320">BUZZING</p>
                       <p begin="0:24:41.600" end="0:24:46.880">But for some insects, defence is a much more complicated affair.</p>
                       <p begin="0:24:48.920" end="0:24:52.640">An oogpister beetle in South Africa.</p>
                       <p begin="0:24:52.680" end="0:24:54.960">He hunts ants.</p>
                       <p begin="0:25:03.560" end="0:25:07.040">Eating ants may give him more than just nourishment.</p>
                       <p begin="0:25:07.080" end="0:25:11.280">He may get something else from them that helps him fight his enemies.</p>
                       <p begin="0:25:22.200" end="0:25:28.080">The ants launch a counter-attack and nip his ankles.</p>
                       <p begin="0:25:28.120" end="0:25:31.320">But he simply kicks them out of the way.</p>
                       <p begin="0:25:41.800" end="0:25:44.720">The valiantants drive him off...</p>
                       <p begin="0:25:44.760" end="0:25:47.760">straight into real danger.</p>
                       <p begin="0:25:51.560" end="0:25:53.040">A mongoose.</p>
                       <p begin="0:25:58.040" end="0:26:01.200">It's inquisitive.</p>
                       <p begin="0:26:01.240" end="0:26:05.520">But it's also wary of the oogpister.</p>
                       <p begin="0:26:05.560" end="0:26:09.320">A black and white pattern is a warning signal.</p>
                       <p begin="0:26:09.360" end="0:26:11.320">The beetle takes aim...</p>
                       <p begin="0:26:15.120" end="0:26:19.440">And fires formic acid straight at the mongoose's eyes and mouth.</p>
                       <p begin="0:26:24.720" end="0:26:27.840">The beetle probably collected this acid from the ants.</p>
                       <p begin="0:26:27.880" end="0:26:34.400">It certainly makes the beetle itself very distasteful and that, in turn, makes it worth mimicking.</p>
                       <p begin="0:26:34.440" end="0:26:39.000">This defenceless little lizard carries the beetles' warning pattern.</p>
                       <p begin="0:26:40.960" end="0:26:44.960">It also imitates the way the beetle runs.</p>
                       <p begin="0:26:46.960" end="0:26:50.480">Not particularly well, it's true, but well enough to</p>
                       <p begin="0:26:50.520" end="0:26:55.360">fool predators into thinking it just might be an acid-firing beetle.</p>
                       <p begin="0:27:05.000" end="0:27:10.160">All kinds of insects have developed chemical weapons.</p>
                       <p begin="0:27:12.480" end="0:27:15.720">A pair of devil-rider stick insects.</p>
                       <p begin="0:27:18.840" end="0:27:23.400">They fire bitter-tasting oils, terpenes.</p>
                       <p begin="0:27:27.480" end="0:27:32.040">European wood ants under attack from a hungry crow.</p>
                       <p begin="0:27:32.080" end="0:27:37.120">They fire the sort of acid that gives nettles their sting,</p>
                       <p begin="0:27:37.160" end="0:27:39.920">so this is like one of us falling into a nettle patch.</p>
                       <p begin="0:27:50.400" end="0:27:55.440">But the master of chemical warfare is the bombardier beetle.</p>
                       <p begin="0:27:56.320" end="0:28:00.440">It can create a chemical reaction within it's body so violent</p>
                       <p begin="0:28:00.480" end="0:28:05.240">that boiling caustic liquid explodes out of its abdomen.</p>
                       <p begin="0:28:13.840" end="0:28:16.280">By pulsing the jet 500 times a second,</p>
                       <p begin="0:28:16.320" end="0:28:20.760">it keeps its rear end just cool enough to prevent it being cooked.</p>
                       <p begin="0:28:39.360" end="0:28:41.480">In the woodlands of Minnesota,</p>
                       <p begin="0:28:41.520" end="0:28:46.240">there is an insect that has another chemical weapon.</p>
                       <p begin="0:28:46.280" end="0:28:52.040">But this one fights as an army and can stand up to almost any predator.</p>
                       <p begin="0:29:01.800" end="0:29:07.800">Bees collect nectar all day and transform it, within their stomachs,</p>
                       <p begin="0:29:07.840" end="0:29:11.360">into one of nature's richest foods, honey.</p>
                       <p begin="0:29:15.680" end="0:29:21.720">Hundreds of them are bringing their precious loads back to their colony in this hollow log.</p>
                       <p begin="0:29:31.720" end="0:29:36.320">The honey in their combs provides food for their young</p>
                       <p begin="0:29:36.360" end="0:29:41.280">and for the whole colony if the weatherturns cold or there's a drought.</p>
                       <p begin="0:29:53.960" end="0:29:59.280">But so much food attracts thieves.</p>
                       <p begin="0:30:01.280" end="0:30:04.560">A black bear cub has a sweet tooth.</p>
                       <p begin="0:30:08.040" end="0:30:10.360">But he's never come across bees before</p>
                       <p begin="0:30:10.400" end="0:30:13.960">and he doesn't know that they will defend their honey to the death.</p>
                       <p begin="0:30:18.680" end="0:30:22.400">Stinging is the ultimate self-sacrifice for a bee,</p>
                       <p begin="0:30:22.440" end="0:30:25.840">because itcan't pull out its barbed sting.</p>
                       <p begin="0:30:28.280" end="0:30:31.000">So its body is torn apart.</p>
                       <p begin="0:30:43.320" end="0:30:46.440">The bees' attack was far too much for the cub.</p>
                       <p begin="0:30:48.240" end="0:30:50.600">But a greater challenge is coming.</p>
                       <p begin="0:30:54.960" end="0:30:56.440">The cub's mother!</p>
                       <p begin="0:30:58.240" end="0:31:00.240">ANGRY BUZZING</p>
                       <p begin="0:31:03.880" end="0:31:09.280">The bees fight so hard that she only has time to steal a single comb.</p>
                       <p begin="0:31:17.960" end="0:31:21.600">While the family enjoy their honey at a safe distance,</p>
                       <p begin="0:31:21.640" end="0:31:24.800">the beesappear to have been defeated.</p>
                       <p begin="0:31:32.240" end="0:31:34.000">Their home has been destroyed</p>
                       <p begin="0:31:34.040" end="0:31:37.520">and their young will inevitably die out in the open.</p>
                       <p begin="0:31:37.560" end="0:31:44.160">Yet the colony is not doomed because the workers are now rescuing at least some of what really matters...</p>
                       <p begin="0:31:45.640" end="0:31:46.760">..their honey.</p>
                       <p begin="0:31:49.880" end="0:31:55.480">Each survivor is able to eat its own weight in honey, storing it in its stomach.</p>
                       <p begin="0:32:02.240" end="0:32:04.800">They will have to abandon their dying young,</p>
                       <p begin="0:32:04.840" end="0:32:07.760">but they will take much of their precious honey with them</p>
                       <p begin="0:32:07.800" end="0:32:11.520">to sustain themselves while they build a new colony.</p>
                       <p begin="0:32:14.960" end="0:32:21.000">Working together in such an organised society is the insects' great innovation.</p>
                       <p begin="0:32:22.560" end="0:32:25.200">So how did it begin?</p>
                       <p begin="0:32:32.040" end="0:32:35.320">It may have started in a place like this -</p>
                       <p begin="0:32:35.360" end="0:32:38.520">the nest of the Japanese red bug.</p>
                       <p begin="0:32:42.120" end="0:32:48.400">Parent insects don't usually care for their offspring but this bug is different.</p>
                       <p begin="0:32:54.240" end="0:32:59.760">The young feed on fallen fruit from just one kind of rare tree.</p>
                       <p begin="0:33:04.640" end="0:33:10.120">They could neverfind it by themselves. So theirmother collects it for them.</p>
                       <p begin="0:33:25.160" end="0:33:29.000">She probes every fruit she finds</p>
                       <p begin="0:33:29.040" end="0:33:32.800">to test its ripeness</p>
                       <p begin="0:33:32.840" end="0:33:34.840">and rejects one after another.</p>
                       <p begin="0:33:36.520" end="0:33:39.280">This can take hours.</p>
                       <p begin="0:33:42.560" end="0:33:45.640">At last, a perfect fruit.</p>
                       <p begin="0:33:53.800" end="0:33:54.840">A thief!</p>
                       <p begin="0:33:54.880" end="0:33:58.160">It's easier to steal than find food for yourself.</p>
                       <p begin="0:34:00.640" end="0:34:06.760">For both bugs, the outcome of this dispute will be life-changing.</p>
                       <p begin="0:34:09.880" end="0:34:13.080">As the mother struggles to keep herprize,</p>
                       <p begin="0:34:13.120" end="0:34:16.840">her young, back in the nest, are growing restless.</p>
                       <p begin="0:34:22.640" end="0:34:25.680">The thief has won.</p>
                       <p begin="0:34:25.720" end="0:34:32.400">The mother doesn't know that her hungry young are leaving their nest in search of a better provider.</p>
                       <p begin="0:34:40.120" end="0:34:42.880">She returns</p>
                       <p begin="0:34:42.920" end="0:34:45.840">to find that her nest is empty.</p>
                       <p begin="0:34:56.120" end="0:35:01.920">Her young find the nest of the thief, who is herself a mother.</p>
                       <p begin="0:35:04.280" end="0:35:10.040">She returns to find that she has twice as many mouths to feed.</p>
                       <p begin="0:35:15.440" end="0:35:20.200">The loser has failed at her only chance of parenthood.</p>
                       <p begin="0:35:25.480" end="0:35:29.800">For the thief, life has suddenly got much harder.</p>
                       <p begin="0:35:29.840" end="0:35:33.360">A fruitwon't now last as long as it did.</p>
                       <p begin="0:35:34.360" end="0:35:38.040">The youngclamber over her, demanding more.</p>
                       <p begin="0:35:58.000" end="0:36:01.640">She returns with another fruit but her enlarged and</p>
                       <p begin="0:36:01.680" end="0:36:04.760">insatiable brood want still more.</p>
                       <p begin="0:36:07.080" end="0:36:10.840">So she has towork non-stop, day after day.</p>
                       <p begin="0:36:24.400" end="0:36:29.120">At last, the young become big enough to fend for themselves.</p>
                       <p begin="0:36:29.160" end="0:36:32.200">But their success has come at a cost.</p>
                       <p begin="0:36:32.240" end="0:36:35.880">The mother has worked herself to death.</p>
                       <p begin="0:36:36.880" end="0:36:43.520">And now her body hasbecome their last meal before they leave home.</p>
                       <p begin="0:36:45.160" end="0:36:47.200">Looking after the young in such a way</p>
                       <p begin="0:36:47.240" end="0:36:52.040">is thought to be the first step towards living in a community.</p>
                       <p begin="0:36:58.040" end="0:37:03.400">But some insects benefit from doing the opposite of collaborating.</p>
                       <p begin="0:37:03.440" end="0:37:05.120">They kill one another.</p>
                       <p begin="0:37:07.520" end="0:37:10.680">Dawson's bee is one of the largest in the world.</p>
                       <p begin="0:37:13.520" end="0:37:17.640">It nests in the baked soil of the Australian outback.</p>
                       <p begin="0:37:17.680" end="0:37:23.120">Flowers are rare in thisdesert, so colonies of these bees are few and far between.</p>
                       <p begin="0:37:31.080" end="0:37:35.000">The bees excavate tunnels fortheir young.</p>
                       <p begin="0:37:45.120" end="0:37:49.560">The community is so harmonious that it's hard to believe that this place</p>
                       <p begin="0:37:49.600" end="0:37:52.720">is also the setting for mass murder.</p>
                       <p begin="0:37:56.880" end="0:38:01.320">Tempers do flare when a bee gets confused and goes down another's burrow.</p>
                       <p begin="0:38:01.360" end="0:38:04.200">But these are minor disagreements.</p>
                       <p begin="0:38:08.720" end="0:38:14.840">The colony is peaceful at the moment becauseevery bee here is a female.</p>
                       <p begin="0:38:14.880" end="0:38:19.200">It's the males that are the killers and they are all dead.</p>
                       <p begin="0:38:23.520" end="0:38:25.720">Their story began two monthsearlier,</p>
                       <p begin="0:38:25.760" end="0:38:28.440">before theappearance of the females.</p>
                       <p begin="0:38:31.760" end="0:38:34.480">Male Dawson's bees.</p>
                       <p begin="0:38:41.440" end="0:38:46.080">The females are only just emerging, burrowing their way, one by one,</p>
                       <p begin="0:38:46.120" end="0:38:49.280">out of the tunnels where they hatched and grew up</p>
                       <p begin="0:38:49.320" end="0:38:51.680">and their scent enflames the males.</p>
                       <p begin="0:38:54.080" end="0:38:57.440">They arehuge and built for fighting.</p>
                       <p begin="0:38:59.440" end="0:39:03.800">And each one wants to be in the best position to mate with a female.</p>
                       <p begin="0:39:20.160" end="0:39:23.520">A female emerges and immediately there's a brawl</p>
                       <p begin="0:39:23.560" end="0:39:25.760">as every male tries to reach her.</p>
                       <p begin="0:39:27.280" end="0:39:31.080">It's very rare for animals to kill their own kind in combat,</p>
                       <p begin="0:39:31.120" end="0:39:33.960">but stinging and biting rivals to death</p>
                       <p begin="0:39:34.000" end="0:39:38.760">is usually the only way these male bees get a female.</p>
                       <p begin="0:39:49.720" end="0:39:54.640">A winner manages to claim a female and the pair race for cover.</p>
                       <p begin="0:39:56.520" end="0:40:01.720">Meanwhile, the female's lingering scent drives one unsuccessful male</p>
                       <p begin="0:40:01.760" end="0:40:03.320">into a deadly frenzy.</p>
                       <p begin="0:40:05.080" end="0:40:11.360">Another female, caught in the middle of another brawl, becomes an accidental casualty.</p>
                       <p begin="0:40:18.240" end="0:40:23.840">By the time the last female has emerged, every male is dead.</p>
                       <p begin="0:40:23.880" end="0:40:29.560">The battles have ensured that the strongest males will have mated with the most females.</p>
                       <p begin="0:40:33.920" end="0:40:37.800">Two months later and it's an all female world</p>
                       <p begin="0:40:37.840" end="0:40:41.200">with thenext generation already developing underground.</p>
                       <p begin="0:41:04.040" end="0:41:08.960">Insects have evolved sophisticated societies that, in complexity,</p>
                       <p begin="0:41:09.000" end="0:41:12.960">are the closest thing in nature to our own cities.</p>
                       <p begin="0:41:24.640" end="0:41:28.520">The insects that built this structure in Argentina</p>
                       <p begin="0:41:28.560" end="0:41:35.520">dominate the surrounding grasslands thanks to skills that seem almost more human than insect.</p>
                       <p begin="0:41:40.400" end="0:41:42.680">It's a metropolis,</p>
                       <p begin="0:41:42.720" end="0:41:46.040">a home to millions of ants.</p>
                       <p begin="0:41:48.600" end="0:41:51.960">The colony needs a huge supply of food.</p>
                       <p begin="0:41:52.960" end="0:41:55.640">It's surrounded by grass,</p>
                       <p begin="0:41:55.680" end="0:41:59.040">but the ants themselves can't digest a blade of it.</p>
                       <p begin="0:42:00.920" end="0:42:03.840">Nonetheless, they collect it.</p>
                       <p begin="0:42:05.920" end="0:42:11.240">Although they're all the same species, they exist in different shapes and sizes.</p>
                       <p begin="0:42:17.520" end="0:42:22.440">The heads of these big-jawed individuals are not full of brain...</p>
                       <p begin="0:42:22.480" end="0:42:24.280">but brawn.</p>
                       <p begin="0:42:24.320" end="0:42:26.920">They give the species its name.</p>
                       <p begin="0:42:26.960" end="0:42:28.440">They are grass cutters.</p>
                       <p begin="0:42:37.400" end="0:42:41.040">They work all day, every day.</p>
                       <p begin="0:43:09.120" end="0:43:13.200">The smaller ants, down on the ground, are porters with the job</p>
                       <p begin="0:43:13.240" end="0:43:16.440">of carrying the grass segments back to the colony.</p>
                       <p begin="0:43:28.080" end="0:43:33.600">They have great strength. Their main problem is balance.</p>
                       <p begin="0:44:00.360" end="0:44:05.920">Columns of them carry the grass back to the nest along highways</p>
                       <p begin="0:44:05.960" end="0:44:08.120">as straight as Roman roads.</p>
                       <p begin="0:44:14.040" end="0:44:20.160">Different members of the colony specialise in particular tasks inmuch the same way as people do.</p>
                       <p begin="0:44:24.440" end="0:44:28.200">But, as in human society, there can be problems.</p>
                       <p begin="0:44:29.200" end="0:44:32.320">A hitch-hiker makes one ant's job much harder.</p>
                       <p begin="0:44:34.000" end="0:44:36.840">And this isn't even grass.</p>
                       <p begin="0:44:58.640" end="0:45:03.040">A single colony harvests half a tonneof grass a year,</p>
                       <p begin="0:45:03.080" end="0:45:06.360">more thanany other animal on these plains.</p>
                       <p begin="0:45:06.400" end="0:45:10.360">But since they themselves can't eat it, why do they do so?</p>
                       <p begin="0:45:16.960" end="0:45:19.760">The answer lies underground.</p>
                       <p begin="0:45:19.800" end="0:45:25.040">They haveone of most extraordinary survivalstrategies in the insect world.</p>
                       <p begin="0:45:27.560" end="0:45:30.400">The ants have dug a network oftunnels</p>
                       <p begin="0:45:30.440" end="0:45:34.200">that extend downwards for over seven metres.</p>
                       <p begin="0:45:38.560" end="0:45:44.040">At the heart of the colony lies the key to their survival. A fungus.</p>
                       <p begin="0:45:44.080" end="0:45:46.600">But this isn't sloppy house-keeping.</p>
                       <p begin="0:45:46.640" end="0:45:49.880">This is a fungus that is found nowhere else on earth.</p>
                       <p begin="0:45:53.840" end="0:45:57.720">And the ants cultivate it assiduously.</p>
                       <p begin="0:45:57.760" end="0:46:02.160">The big-jawed ants chop up the grass covering it with an</p>
                       <p begin="0:46:02.200" end="0:46:07.400">antibiotic saliva that kills every kind of fungus except this one.</p>
                       <p begin="0:46:10.160" end="0:46:14.280">The ants are farmers.</p>
                       <p begin="0:46:14.320" end="0:46:16.560">They feed the grass to the fungus</p>
                       <p begin="0:46:16.600" end="0:46:18.200">and the fungus thrives.</p>
                       <p begin="0:46:22.840" end="0:46:28.240">The ants cultivate dozens of these fungus gardens throughout the colony.</p>
                       <p begin="0:46:29.440" end="0:46:32.760">This is what they eat.</p>
                       <p begin="0:46:32.800" end="0:46:39.040">The system is so efficient that a single colony can have five million members.</p>
                       <p begin="0:46:40.840" end="0:46:43.680">But the fungus is also dangerous.</p>
                       <p begin="0:46:46.360" end="0:46:52.440">As it grows it releases carbon dioxide that could asphyxiate the entire colony.</p>
                       <p begin="0:46:53.840" end="0:46:57.520">The ants' way of dealing with this danger is ingenious.</p>
                       <p begin="0:46:59.480" end="0:47:05.120">They construct their nest so that it has an automatic air-conditioning system.</p>
                       <p begin="0:47:06.680" end="0:47:10.640">The outer surface is so shaped thatthe slightest breeze</p>
                       <p begin="0:47:10.680" end="0:47:14.480">sucks out staleair through these central vents.</p>
                       <p begin="0:47:14.520" end="0:47:19.200">At the same time, fresh air is drawn down through the outer vents,</p>
                       <p begin="0:47:19.240" end="0:47:21.720">right into the heart of the nest.</p>
                       <p begin="0:47:27.480" end="0:47:31.400">Our own societies have existed for thousands of years</p>
                       <p begin="0:47:31.440" end="0:47:36.280">but insectsocieties have lasted for millions.</p>
                       <p begin="0:47:44.760" end="0:47:49.320">There may be ten million different kinds of insects</p>
                       <p begin="0:47:49.360" end="0:47:54.680">and there are 200 million individuals for every one of us.</p>
                       <p begin="0:47:57.160" end="0:48:00.920">The insects' flexible armour and their adaptability</p>
                       <p begin="0:48:00.960" end="0:48:06.960">has made them the most abundant andthe most diverse animal group in our planet's history.</p>
                       <p begin="0:48:29.960" end="0:48:32.440">The Sierra Madre Mountains in Mexico</p>
                       <p begin="0:48:32.480" end="0:48:35.560">are home to one of the greatest natural wonders.</p>
                       <p begin="0:48:39.040" end="0:48:45.520">A billion bright orange butterflies offered the Life team a wonderful filming challenge.</p>
                       <p begin="0:48:48.880" end="0:48:53.160">The colonies are only found above 3,000 metres</p>
                       <p begin="0:48:53.200" end="0:48:57.480">and the team trek there slowly in the thin air.</p>
                       <p begin="0:49:09.120" end="0:49:15.480">The monarch phenomenon was only discovered here around 30 years ago and one man has been studying</p>
                       <p begin="0:49:15.520" end="0:49:19.160">them every year since, Professor Lincoln Brower.</p>
                       <p begin="0:49:19.200" end="0:49:23.200">His knowledge will be essential if the team are to achieve their goal</p>
                       <p begin="0:49:23.240" end="0:49:27.640">of flying a camera among the butterflies.</p>
                       <p begin="0:49:27.680" end="0:49:30.560">It's amazing that the butterflies only come to this area</p>
                       <p begin="0:49:30.600" end="0:49:34.040">that's about 30 by 60 miles in extent.</p>
                       <p begin="0:49:34.080" end="0:49:38.520">There are other areas that have high forests,</p>
                       <p begin="0:49:38.560" end="0:49:43.400">in different parts of Mexico, to the west of here, to the south of here,</p>
                       <p begin="0:49:43.440" end="0:49:49.760">but as far as we know, this is the only place that monarchs are able to spend the winter.</p>
                       <p begin="0:49:49.800" end="0:49:54.200">The butterflies are in such numbers that filming them the traditional way,</p>
                       <p begin="0:49:54.240" end="0:49:58.240">from a camera on a tripod, is reasonably straightforward.</p>
                       <p begin="0:49:58.280" end="0:50:02.840">But to get a butterfly's viewpoint by flying a camera amongst</p>
                       <p begin="0:50:02.880" end="0:50:06.680">the swarms is going to be altogether more difficult.</p>
                       <p begin="0:50:09.120" end="0:50:14.560">First, the team need a spot where butterflies gather in huge numbers.</p>
                       <p begin="0:50:17.760" end="0:50:23.760">Luckily, Lincoln knows a place where thousands come down to drink every day.</p>
                       <p begin="0:50:23.800" end="0:50:28.520">The crew spend the next three days preparing the equipment -</p>
                       <p begin="0:50:28.560" end="0:50:35.120">a remote-controlled camera, a lot of cable, two bicycle wheels, a bag of rocks and some muscle-power.</p>
                       <p begin="0:50:38.880" end="0:50:45.320">Now all they need to do is wait until the butterfly numbers reach truly impressive proportions.</p>
                       <p begin="0:50:50.080" end="0:50:53.440">By mid-day, the butterflies are swarming</p>
                       <p begin="0:50:53.480" end="0:50:57.160">and it's time for the camera to glide with them through the air.</p>
                       <p begin="0:50:57.200" end="0:50:58.680">Three and away.</p>
                       <p begin="0:51:10.640" end="0:51:14.040">Superb. OK, let's just stop that.</p>
                       <p begin="0:51:14.080" end="0:51:15.760">Absolutely stunning.</p>
                       <p begin="0:51:15.800" end="0:51:18.400">We've got great numbers coming in. Let's keep going</p>
                       <p begin="0:51:18.440" end="0:51:21.360">and then we'll do a turn round shot.</p>
                       <p begin="0:51:21.400" end="0:51:26.640">A series of unique shots flying withthe butterflies.</p>
                       <p begin="0:51:31.560" end="0:51:35.040">But that was the easy part.</p>
                       <p begin="0:51:36.600" end="0:51:41.600">Now it's time to get the camera 50 metres up into the tree tops.</p>
                       <p begin="0:51:43.160" end="0:51:49.440">Filming the roosting butterflies is not going to be simple, the clusters are unstable.</p>
                       <p begin="0:51:50.640" end="0:51:53.320">And they can suddenly disperse without warning,</p>
                       <p begin="0:51:53.360" end="0:51:55.320">what Lincoln calls an explosion!</p>
                       <p begin="0:51:55.360" end="0:51:58.920">Here'sanother explosion. Wow, look at that!</p>
                       <p begin="0:51:58.960" end="0:52:01.480">And they're going right over our head.</p>
                       <p begin="0:52:03.240" end="0:52:09.360">Spectacular, no doubt, but a real problem for the climbing team, Jim Spickler and Tim Fogg.</p>
                       <p begin="0:52:09.400" end="0:52:11.880">Would it be better for us to start now?</p>
                       <p begin="0:52:11.920" end="0:52:14.360">we're gonna be very careful not to disturb them,</p>
                       <p begin="0:52:14.400" end="0:52:18.080">or limit our disturbance, but if we do disturb them right now</p>
                       <p begin="0:52:18.120" end="0:52:22.960">it seems that they're warm enough that they could relocate to a cluster right adjacent to them,</p>
                       <p begin="0:52:23.000" end="0:52:24.640">do you think that's true?</p>
                       <p begin="0:52:24.680" end="0:52:30.240">Well, if you disturb them they tend to fly away from the tree, 50 feet or so,</p>
                       <p begin="0:52:30.280" end="0:52:34.640">so you'll lose those clusters I think if you disturb them.</p>
                       <p begin="0:52:34.680" end="0:52:40.720">Do you think they'll cluster again though, tomorrow night?Idoubt it.</p>
                       <p begin="0:52:40.760" end="0:52:42.400">&lt; I think they'll just move down.</p>
                       <p begin="0:52:42.440" end="0:52:50.240">That's really hard stuff, you know because I can't seehow we can get up the trees</p>
                       <p begin="0:52:50.280" end="0:52:51.840">and do what we have to up there,</p>
                       <p begin="0:52:51.880" end="0:52:54.360">close to any clusters without them flying.</p>
                       <p begin="0:52:54.400" end="0:52:58.200">I just don't know how I'm gonna be able to get an arrow into the tree.</p>
                       <p begin="0:52:58.240" end="0:53:01.680">I think if you picked your tree, you could put the arrow in it now.</p>
                       <p begin="0:53:03.000" end="0:53:07.800">The prospect of rigging cables high in the canopy, without disturbing</p>
                       <p begin="0:53:07.840" end="0:53:13.800">the butterflies is a daunting one. They may only get one chance.</p>
                       <p begin="0:53:13.840" end="0:53:15.680">One false move and it'll all be gone.</p>
                       <p begin="0:53:15.720" end="0:53:18.200">I had the impression that they might come back but</p>
                       <p begin="0:53:18.240" end="0:53:21.680">Lincoln says they just won't, they'll just move on to another tree.</p>
                       <p begin="0:53:21.720" end="0:53:24.600">So we put all the rigging in, disturb them and then...</p>
                       <p begin="0:53:24.640" end="0:53:26.600">that's it!</p>
                       <p begin="0:53:26.640" end="0:53:30.840">Choosing which trees to rig is a critical decision.</p>
                       <p begin="0:53:33.440" end="0:53:36.880">Can you get right to tree number six do you think, or is that too far?</p>
                       <p begin="0:53:43.880" end="0:53:48.040">They begin by firing a line over a suitably high branch.</p>
                       <p begin="0:53:58.320" end="0:53:59.800">That'll work.</p>
                       <p begin="0:54:02.440" end="0:54:07.400">Nobody, not even Lincoln, knows how the butterflies will react.</p>
                       <p begin="0:54:12.320" end="0:54:14.760">Yeah that's gonna work perfect, I think.</p>
                       <p begin="0:54:14.800" end="0:54:16.720">OK, great.</p>
                       <p begin="0:54:16.760" end="0:54:19.600">I've got to do a changeover here so just give me a moment.</p>
                       <p begin="0:54:26.680" end="0:54:29.080">There's an explosion.</p>
                       <p begin="0:54:34.480" end="0:54:39.160">Thankfully, it's not in the trees that Jim and Tim are rigging with such care.</p>
                       <p begin="0:54:49.040" end="0:54:51.680">Can you just push it towards me a bit?</p>
                       <p begin="0:54:51.720" end="0:54:53.480">Ouch.You OK?</p>
                       <p begin="0:54:53.520" end="0:54:56.560">Yep.OK, get your fingers out.</p>
                       <p begin="0:54:56.600" end="0:54:58.600">OK, that's good.</p>
                       <p begin="0:55:00.320" end="0:55:07.000">It takes another three days to get theaerial rig set up, followed by many hours of fine tuning.</p>
                       <p begin="0:55:07.040" end="0:55:10.600">Just pan it so we don't see it in the monitor, please.</p>
                       <p begin="0:55:15.600" end="0:55:20.560">Everything is finally set and the butterflies are still there.</p>
                       <p begin="0:55:20.600" end="0:55:24.080">One, two, three.</p>
                       <p begin="0:55:28.200" end="0:55:29.680">Take one.</p>
                       <p begin="0:55:37.560" end="0:55:39.160">Too slow.</p>
                       <p begin="0:55:39.200" end="0:55:41.160">There was no load at the beginning</p>
                       <p begin="0:55:41.200" end="0:55:44.400">and thensuddenly it just completely stopped.</p>
                       <p begin="0:55:48.000" end="0:55:50.880">Take six.</p>
                       <p begin="0:55:50.920" end="0:55:55.680">Keep going. Start to slow, slow and keep going, keep going, keep going.</p>
                       <p begin="0:55:55.720" end="0:55:57.440">OK, Mike, hold it.</p>
                       <p begin="0:55:57.480" end="0:55:59.520">Not far enough.</p>
                       <p begin="0:55:59.560" end="0:56:01.960">We've not got enough weight, Jim.</p>
                       <p begin="0:56:10.600" end="0:56:12.040">Take nine.</p>
                       <p begin="0:56:12.080" end="0:56:13.400">Go on, Mike.</p>
                       <p begin="0:56:13.440" end="0:56:17.400">Go on, Mike. Get in close, Mike, now start slowing.</p>
                       <p begin="0:56:17.440" end="0:56:18.720">OK.</p>
                       <p begin="0:56:18.760" end="0:56:23.120">It's still not right and now time is running out.</p>
                       <p begin="0:56:23.160" end="0:56:25.000">I think the light's going.</p>
                       <p begin="0:56:25.040" end="0:56:27.240">Shall we do one last take?</p>
                       <p begin="0:56:27.280" end="0:56:31.520">All right. Because these ones here, we're losing the light on them.</p>
                       <p begin="0:56:31.560" end="0:56:34.520">Try and get a shot that's going past here if it's smooth.</p>
                       <p begin="0:56:36.520" end="0:56:41.040">One, two, three, and we're away.</p>
                       <p begin="0:56:41.080" end="0:56:42.720">Take 17.</p>
                       <p begin="0:56:48.400" end="0:56:50.800">And it's looking good.</p>
                       <p begin="0:56:50.840" end="0:56:56.280">OK, start slowing, Mike. OK, keep it going, keep it going.</p>
                       <p begin="0:56:59.200" end="0:57:01.240">Success at last.</p>
                       <p begin="0:57:05.320" end="0:57:09.920">With the technique now working, the crew rig more and more shots</p>
                       <p begin="0:57:09.960" end="0:57:14.880">to give an aerial perspective on the monarch phenomenon.</p>
                       <p begin="0:57:20.840" end="0:57:25.720">His work advising the crew over, Lincoln continues the observations</p>
                       <p begin="0:57:25.760" end="0:57:28.600">he's been making for over a quarter of a century.</p>
                       <p begin="0:57:28.640" end="0:57:31.800">Although the butterflies are still here in immense numbers,</p>
                       <p begin="0:57:31.840" end="0:57:35.680">he's worried there is a threat to their survival.</p>
                       <p begin="0:57:35.720" end="0:57:42.200">The big, huge influx, maybe sometimes as many as two billion butterflies,</p>
                       <p begin="0:57:42.240" end="0:57:46.360">flying down into this tiny area of 30 by 60 miles,</p>
                       <p begin="0:57:46.400" end="0:57:50.880">is thoroughly endangered by illegal logging.</p>
                       <p begin="0:57:50.920" end="0:57:54.800">If the forest is not protected the phenomenon will be lost.</p>
                       <p begin="0:58:06.800" end="0:58:08.120">It'd be a disaster.</p>
                       <p begin="0:58:08.400" end="0:58:15.000">I mean, it would be like taking the Mona Lisa out of the Parisian museum and,</p>
                       <p begin="0:58:15.040" end="0:58:16.600">and burning it up.</p>
                       <p begin="0:58:34.440" end="0:58:36.440">Subtitles by Red Bee Media Ltd</p>

    	</div>
  	</body>
</tt>


